American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIc. 1826-1836 APS.Archives.IIc APS.Archives.IIc
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Not Found
    - Letter to Mrs. Rivardi, Aug. 20, 21, 1826; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Resumé of A.L. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 57.) Forwards publications.
    - Memoranda, March 27-30, [1826]; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      A.D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee. Letterbooks, vol. 3, p.46.) Wrote to Lafayette, Mrs. Godon, Mrs. Riviere, Mr. Pichon and Mr. Barnet.
    - Rob[er]t Walsh Jr., May 22, 1827; 5" x 7 7/8"; Walsh, Robert, Jr.
      to John Vaughan, ----, 1 p., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Introducing the Rev. W. B. Sprague.
    - Letter to J[oel] R[oberts] Poinsett, Sept. 5, 1827; 10x8; Exter, Richard
      Mexico, A.L.S. 4p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol.2,no.72b.) Concerning a giant cypress. Cf. Minutes, P.571. Enclosed originally in letter from Poinsett to J. Vaughan;Sept. 6, 1827.
    - Letter to [David Bailie] Warden, July 12, [1832]; 6x4; Debure frères
      L. 1p. and add. In French. Concerning books for the APS.
    - Letter to Jno. Vaughan, Philadelphia, Sept. 6, 1827; 10x8; Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851
      Mexico, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Enc. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 72a.) Concerning the size of a cypress. Cf. Minutes, p.571. For enclosure see: letter from Exter to Poinsett; Sept. 5, 1827.
    - List of books presented to the American philosophical society by Friedrich von Adelung, Nov. 5, 1827; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      D. 1p. (see APS. Historical...committee Letterbooks, vol. 3, p. 61.) For original list, see Adelung; List of books...; Nov. 5, 1827.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Nov. 7, 1827; 15x9-1/2; Anderson, Henry J. (Henry James), 1799-1875
      New York, A.L.S. 8p.,add.,end. 15x9-1/2. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 112.) Concerning the motion of bodies. Cf. Minutes, p.574.
    - Letter to Peter S. DuPonceau, Dec. 20, 1827; 8x4-1/2; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
      Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and add. Enc. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 53.) Friendly letter. Forwards material to the APS. For enclosure, see: [Institute de France.] Moulin sans meule [Dec.1827].
    - Moulin sans meule, Dec., 1827; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Institut de France
      D. 2p. In French. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 53-1/2.) Enclosed originally in letter from Warden to DuPonceau; Dec. 20, 1827.
    - Charges on Ewing's hydrant, , 1827-1841; 7-1/2x4; American Philosophical Society
      D.in hand of John Vaughan. 1p.
    - Letter to R.M. Patterson, Philadelphia, Jan. 27, 1828; 12-1/2x8; Matthews, Thomas Johnston, 1787-1852
      Lexington, A.L.S. 7p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 114.) Concerning a new use of the sextant. Cf. Minutes, p.577.
    - Letter to Robert M. Patterson, Philadelphia, April 19, 1828; 11x9; Hassler, F. R. (Ferdinand Rudolph), 1770-1843
      Richmond, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 78.) Friendly letter, Concerning Copernicus and Kepler.
    - Advertisement about Brewster's milling machine, Oct. 14, 1828; 10x8; Sanseer Machine Co.
      Middletown, Conn., D.S.: Joseph W.Hubbard,Secy. 2p. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 55.) On same sheet with letter from Mease to [Sanseer Machine Co];Nov.11, 1831: and Great Falls Mfg.Co.to E.J.Abel;Oct. 31,1828.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Dec. 17, 1828; 10x8; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, Dec. 17, 1828. A.L.S. 1p. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Mechanics, machinery, eng., etc., no. 54.) Concerning an answer to Rafn's article on Norse antiquities discovered in North America. Cf. Minutes, p.585. On same sheet is memorandum by J. Vaughan; [Dec. 1828].
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Nov. 23, 1829; 10x8; Clibborn, Edward
      Cincinnati, A.L.S. 5p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 82.) Concerning electricity. Refers to Franklin. Cf. Minutes, p.598. FILM54-64 FRAME 116
    - Thermometrical observations, Jan., March, 1829; 8x6; Hodge, Hugh L. (Hugh Lenox), 1796-1873
      D. 4p. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Natural Philosophy, vol. 2, no. 80.) Cf. Minutes, P.592.
    - Thermometrical observations for Feb., 1829, March 21, 1829; 10x8; Hodge, Hugh L. (Hugh Lenox), 1796-1873
      [communicated] D. 3p.,end. Communicated by F.Nichols. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 79.) Cf. Minutes, p.590, 592.
    - Letter to the American philosophical society, April 16, 1830; 10x7-1/2; Browne, Peter A. (Peter Arrell), 1782-1860
      [read] A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 74.) Concerning impressions in a block of marble. Cf. Minutes, p.601.
    - Concerning a new fossil genus of mastodon and a fossil, April 16, 1830; 10x8; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843
      [read] A.D. 10p.,end. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 75.) Cf, Minutes, p.601.
    - Concerning light, May 21, 1830; 12-1/2x8; Saunders, Samuel Hyde
      [read] D.S. 18p.and add.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 84.) Cf. Minutes, p.602. For covering letter see letter from Conrad to Hare; June 15, 1830.
    - Concerning the longitude of Philosophical Hall, Jan. 5, 1830; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Walker, Sears Cook, 1805-1853
      [read] Oct. 18 1833. D. 5p.and end.by A.D.B[ache]. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 2, no.116.) Cf. Minutes, p.640. Printed: APS Trans., n.s., vol. V, 135 ff.
    - Letter to the American philosophical society, Dec. 3, 1829; 12x7-1/2, 12-1/2x8; Jaeckel, Joseph
      Vienna, A.L.S. 10p., end. In German. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol.2, nos.60-61) ----English translation of letter. 2p. Forwards publication and gives abstract of it.
    - Letter to [Robert] Hare, June 15, 1830; 10x8; Conrad, Solomon White, 1779-1831
      A.L.S. 1p.,end. Enc. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 84a.) Forwards paper by S.H.Saunders. For enclosure, see: Saunders, Concerning light; [read] May 21, 1830.
    - Concerning Macuire-Princep's experiments on poisonous plants, Sept. 17, 1830; 10x8; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843
      A.D.S. 1p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 62.) Cf. Minutes, p.604.
    - Researches on the cause of goitre in the mountains of New Granada, Oct., 1830; 12x8; Boussingault, J. B. (Jean Baptiste), 1802-1887
      D.S. 24p. In French. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 53.) Cf. Minutes, p.626. Enclosed originally in letter from Acosta to the Secretary of the APS; May 24, 1832.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Feb. 1, 1831; 9-1/2x8; Hassler, F. R. (Ferdinand Rudolph), 1770-1843
      Washington, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 115.) Friendly letter. Refers to the survey of the coasts of the U.S. Cf. Minutes, p.614.
    - Letter to the Editors of the Journal of Commerce, New York, Feb. 10, 1831; 9x7-1/2; Bridgeman, Elijah Coleman
      Canton, China, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (See Ms.comm. to the APS. Philology, literature etc., vol. 2, no. 62.) Forwards memoir on the Spanish possessions in the Far East.
    - Letter to the Editors of the Journal of Commerce, New York, Feb. 10, 1831; 9x7-1/2; Journal of commerce of New York. Editors. Bridgeman, Elijah Coleman
      Canton, China, A.L.S. 2p.and add. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 62.) Forwards memoir on the Spanish possessions in the Far East.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, April 18, 1831; 10x8; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 63.) Concerning silk culture in America.
    - Letter to the Secretary of the A.P.S., May 24, 1832; 12x8; Acosta, Joaquin, 1800-1852
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 3p.and end. In French. Enc. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 54.) Forwards memoir by Boussingault. Cf. Minutes, p.626. For enc. see: Boussingault. Researches...; Oct. 1830.
    - Letter to [Sanseer Machine co.], Nov. 11, 1831; 10x8; Mease, James, 1771-1846
      Philadelphia, L. 2p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS Mechanics, Machinery, Eng.,etc.,no.55.) Concerning Brewster's milling machine. On same sheet are: Advertisement by Sanseer Machine co; Oct.14,1828: and letter from Great Falls Mfg.co.to Elisha J. Abel;Oct.31,1828
    - Letter to American Philosophical Society, Nov. 11, 1831; 10x8; Mease, James, 1771-1846
      Philadelphia, L. 2p. (see MS Comm. to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no.55.) Concerning Brewster's milling machine. On same sheet: Advertisement by Sanseer Machine Co; Oct.14, 1828, and letter from Great Falls Mfg.Co. to Elisha J. Abel; Oct. 31, 1828. (Prev. cataloged as letter to Sanseer Mach. Co.
    - Minutes, Feb. 13, 1832; 10x8; Athenaeum of Philadelphia
      D.S.: Wm. McIlhenney. 1p. Extract. Sets up committee on library building. Enclosed originally in letter from the Athenaeum to the APS; [Feb. 1832].
    - Letter to John Vaughan, May 9, 1832; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Dahlgren, John Adolphus Bernard, 1809-1870
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 117.) Forwards J.P.Rodrigues observations for the longitude of Portsmouth.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, June 1, 1832; 10x7-1/2; Cuthbert, John A. (John Albert), 1788-1881
      Hamburg, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc.,no. 56.) Forwarded A.P.S. publications.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Sept. 5, 1832; 10x8; Say, Thomas, 1787-1834
      New Harmony, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history,vol.2, no. 78.) Offers to the APS for publication, his work on North American insects. Cf. Minutes, p.627.
    - Account of a gold mine in Georgia, Sept. 15, 1832; 10x7-1/2; Robertson, George, 1790-1874
      Philadelphia, D. Copy. 1p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history vol. 2, no. 80.)
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Oct. 18, 1832; 10x8; Say, Thomas, 1787-1834
      New Harmony, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. Enc. wanting. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 77.) Concerning his work on North American insects. Cf. Minutes, p.628.
    - Letter to Isaac Hays, Philadelphia, Dec. 1, 1832; 10x8; Say, Thomas, 1787-1834
      New Harmony, A.L.S. 3p.and add. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol.2, no. 79.) Concerning North American insects.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Dec. 6, 1832; 10x8; Wuhielhausen, Frederick Jacob
      Bremen, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng.,etc., no. 57.) Forwarded A.P.S. publications.
    - D. B. Warden to John Vaughan, June 3, 5, 1833; 6 7/8" x 8 7/8"; Warden, David Bailie, 1772-1845
      Librarian of A.P.S., Paris, 2 pp., address and endorsement. A.L.S. Regarding a case of books forwarded in February. Book news and comments. Americans in Paris recommend Warden for consul.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Aug. 8, 1833; 10x8; Harris, Thaddeus Mason, 1768-1842
      Dorchester, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 63.) Concerning publications on ruins in Guatemala.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Jan.17, 1833; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Vaughan, William, 1752-1850
      London, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. Contains copy of letter from Francis Baily to W. Vaughan, Jan. 16, 1833. Encloses letter from Francis Baily respecting Hassler's work on weights and measures. Requests him to try to procure additional copies
    - Letter to P.S. DuPonceau, July 19, 1833; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Dunbar, John R. W. (John Richard Woodcock), 1805-1871
      [read] A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. in hand of A.D. Bache. Enc. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 56.) Forwards broadside. On same sheet is letter from Dunbar to Robinson; June 27, 1833.
    - Letter to J[ohn] K[earsley] Mitchell, Aug. 13, 1833; 10x8; Harrington, William H.
      La Grange, Alabama, L. Extract. 4p.and 6 drawings. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 81.) Concerning fossil remains. Cf. Minutes, p.640.
    - Concerning meteors, Nov., 1833; 10x8; Emerson, G. (Gouveneur), 1796-1874
      D. 15p.and end. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no.85.)
    - Concerning the buzzard inhabiting South Carolina, Jan. 20, 1834; 12-1/2x8; Bachman, John, 1790-1874
      Charleston, A.D.S. 16p.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 82.) Cf. Minutes, p.647.
    - Letter to [Marmaduke Burrough?], April 6, 1834; 9-1/2x8; Harry, William Cobb
      Calcutta, L. 2p. Extract. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 83.) Sends prangos grass seeds from India. Cf. Minutes, p.657.
    - Concerning the origin of coal, May 16, 1834; 13x8; Pedder, James, 1775-1859
      [read] D. 4p.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 35.) Cf. Minutes, p.652. (The endorsement on this document reads "1807")
    - Concerning phases of the occultation of Jupiter by the moon, June 27, 1834; 6x7-1/2; Walker, Sears Cook, 1805-1853
      [read] D. 1p.and add.: John Vaughan, end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 118.) Cf. Minutes, p.655.
    - Report of publications committee on S.C. Walker's paper on the longitude of Philosophical Hall, Aug. 6, 1834; 10x8; American Philosophical Society
      A.D.S.: F. Bache. 1p. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Math. and astronomy,vol. 2, no. 116.) On same sheet as Walker; Concerning the longitude of Philosophical Hall; [read] Oct. 18, 1833.
    - Letter to Robert Walsh, Dec. 15, 1834; 10x7-1/2; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, A.L. 7p.and end. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 86.) Concerning Mark Beaufoy and his works.
    - Letter to the President of the APS, Philadelphia, April 25, 1835; 9-1/2x8; Porter, James
      Alabama, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 87.) Concerning the Aurora borealis.
    - Letter to the Secretary of the A.P.S., May 6, 1835; 13x8; Thornton, B.
      Philadelphia; New York, [read] A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2,,no. 119.) Concerning his method of making polygons.
    - Letter to ----, July 3, 1835; 8x6-1/2; R., W.
      L.S.with initials. 4p. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 64.) Concerning the raising of Lucerne [alfalfa].
    - Letter to Petty Vaughan, London, Aug. 14, 1835; 10x8; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. Letterpress copy. 1p. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, 91a.) Concerning missing copies of an almanac
    - Letter to John Vaughan, oCT. 26, 1835; 10x7-1/2; Vaughan, Petty, 1788-1854
      A.L.S. 1p. Forwards boxes. On same sheet as letter from W.Vaughan to John Vaughan; Oct. 20, 1835.
    - Letter to T[homas] F[rancis] Gordon, Nov. 2, 1835; 9x8; Maxwell, Thomas, 1792-1867
      Elmira, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Enc. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 121.) Forwards memoir by G.W.Miller on the cube root. For enclosure, see: Miller. Concise method of extracting the cube root; [ca.Nov.1835.]
    - Concerning the cause of tornados by electrical discharge, Nov. 20, 1835; 12x7-1/2; Hare, Robert, 1781-1858
      [read] A.D. 2p.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 88.) Cf. Minutes, p.677.
    - A concise method of extracting the cube root, Nov., 1835; 12x8; Miller, George W.
      [ca.] D. 2p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 2,no.120) Enclosed originally in letter from Maxwell to T.F.Gordon; Nov. 2, 1835.
    - Description of an improved air-pump, April 1, 1836 (?); 5x8; Joslin, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1796-1861
      [read] A.D.S. 9p.and add.: American philosophical society, and drawing of 1p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no.98.) Reveals himself as the author of the above paper, entered for the Magellanic premium. Cf. Minutes, p.684 (?).
    - Report of committee on paper by Elias Loomis:, May 20, 20th December, 1836, 1842; 10x8; American Philosophical Society
      "Supplementary observations on the storm...[Philadelphia] D.S.: A. D. Bache and R. M. Patterson. 1p., and end. See APS Proc., II, 185. Printed: APS Trans., VIII, 305.
    - Notice respecting the appearance of waterspouts on the Bahama banks., June 11-13, May 29, 1836, 1843; 7 3/4" x 12 3/4"; Taylor, Richard C. (Richard Cowling), 1789-1851
      Includes extracts from diary, 2 pp.and endorsement. Com. Summary of oral communication presented by the author at the centenary celebration of 1843. See Pro., III, 136-137.
    - Statement of accounts with the American philosophical society, Dec. 31, April 14, 1836-1837; 6x8; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      Philadelphia, D.S.: Jacob Snider, jr. 1p.and end.
    - Numerical catalogue of the library of the American philosophical society., , 1836; American Philosophical Society
      301p. sq. 0. (Manuscript) Ms. In f.p. no.1 2 copies: Cop.1, rough copy Cop.2, fair copy. cop 2 folio